Go, today's דף כ"ו, Daf Khaf Vav, we pick up on כ"ה
עמוד ב' Khaf He Amud Bet and
we are talking about the normal weekday way in which they gave
out the עבודות, avodot, the various services, the
bringing of the קרבנות korbanot to the כהנים kohanim for the תמיד,
tamid, for the fixed קרבן. korban.
And we spoke about the first one was for the תרומת הדשן,
terumat hadeshen, the removing of the ashes. The second one was associated
with the morning תמיד, tamid, although the first parts of it were
not that. The first parts of it related
to the שחיטה shechting of the תמיד, tamid, the throwing of the
blood, but then there was the cleaning of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the
cleaning of the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, the cleaning of the מנורה, menorah,
and then it had a whole series of nine כהנים kohanim that
brought the various limbs of the תמיד tamid after it was dismembered
to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And that was divided up into nine כהנים.
kohanim. So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara,
middle of כ"ה עמוד ב'. Khaf He Amud Bet. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. So אמר בן עזאי לפני רבי עקיבא. Amar Ben Azzai Lifne
Rabbi Akiva. So Ben Azzai said to Rabbi Akiva that they would
bring up, smack in the middle of
כ"ה עמוד ב', Khaf He Amud Bet, two-fifths from the bottom, maybe
twenty lines or so, twenty-five lines. So he said to Rabbi Akiva
they would bring, I heard that basically they would bring the תמיד,
tamid, the limbs up to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, up to the כבש.
kevesh. First they would do it to the כבש kevesh and then
we're going to find out in the next משנה mishnah they would
go from the כבש kevesh and bring it actually to the top
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But I heard they would bring it in
the order in which the animal was walking. So now we're going
to get a whole range of different opinions about the order in
which they would bring the limbs of the animal to the כבש.
kevesh. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. כיצד דרך הילוכו?
Keitzad derech hilucho?
According to Ben Azzai that it was brought the way it would
walk, what's the way it would walk?
הראש והרגל, HaRosh veHaRegel, the head and the foot and the hind
footer. If an animal, now I have to tell you I don't
know, I know nothing about animals, but when they walk, do they
first move their hind leg before their foreleg? Or do they move
them in parallel?
Hey, two hind legs.
No, one hind leg, but one hind leg.
It depends on the animal at the particular size. They didn't know
this until they actually had filmed it.
This said, interesting, this says so first a hind leg, the right
hind leg and then the head. The head obviously juts forward first
and then propelled by the right hind leg, so that would be
the first thing that moves. Then החזה והגרה, HaChazeh veHaGerah, the chest
and the throat because obviously that's moving together with the top of
the body, which is connected to the head. שתי ידים, Shte Yadoyim,
then the two forearms would move. Then שתי דפנות, Shte Defanot, the
two flanks, because presumably they would be propelled forward by the forward
movement of the two forearms. האוקץ והרגל, HaOkatz veHaRegel, and then the
tail and the back and the left hind leg. So this is
sort of how he saw the movement of an animal and the
same way it would move in life, you would bring it to
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. רבי
יוסי אומר דרך הפשטו היה קרב. Rabbi Yose omer derech hafshato haya
karev. No, it would not be brought to the ramp the way
it would move. It would be brought to the ramp the way
they would flay it. So basically and they would flay it from
the bottom of the, they would hang it by its legs and
flay it from the legs down to the head. So how would
they flay it?
כיצד דרך הפשטו? Keitzad derech hafshato? How would they flay it? הראש,
HaRosh, the head. Not that they would flay the head, they would
sever the head, but we're going to see in a minute anyway
you always want to bring the head first, that's symbolically significant and
maybe because it doesn't need to be flayed, that gets brought first.
And then והרגל האוקץ והרגל. veHaRegel HaOkatz veHaRegel. So now we actually
start with both of the hind legs because you're flaying it from
the legs down. So one leg and the tail, or the rear,
the rump, and then the other leg. So you're flaying it, again,
you're hanging it by its legs and flaying it. שתי דפנות, Shte
Defanot, so now you're working from the back to the front other
than having the head separate. So then the two flanks. שתי ידים,
Shte Yadoyim, the two forelegs. החזה והגרה, HaChazeh veHaGerah, and then the
chest and the throat. Fine, that's what he would say. רבי עקיבא
אומר דרך ניתוחו היה קרב, Rabbi Akiva omer derech nitucho haya karev,
the way they would dismember it. Now, does that seem to be
a little bit their choice how they're going to dismember it? So
it sort of a little bit begs the question to why do
you choose to dismember it in a particular way? We understand that
there's a natural way to flay it. Again, I'm not a butcher,
there might be a natural way to dismember an animal when you're
chopping it up. But that's what he says. They would dismember, there
would be a way they would dismember it and they would follow
that pattern in bringing it to the altar.
כיצד דרך ניתוחו? Keitzad derech nitucho? What was the way they would
dismember it? הראש והרגל, HaRosh veHaRegel, first they sever the head, then
הרגל, HaRegel, then the one hind leg, שתי ידים, Shte Yadoyim, two
forelegs, החזה והגרה, HaChazeh veHaGerah, the chest and the throat, שתי דפנות,
Shte Defanot, the two. the two flanks, העוקץ והרגל, Ha'oketz v'haregel, and
then the tail and the hind leg. So that's very similar to
בן עזאי, Ben Azai, I'll allow you to do the comparison yourself,
basically there's a difference between where
the where the two forearms set fit into that order. But that's
a very similar order to that of בן עזאי Ben Azai that
said it would be the way it would walk. רבי יוסי הגלילי
אומר דרך עילויו היה קרב. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer derech iluyo haya
karev. So the way it would go up. Now again, what does
that mean go up?
So actually, I said that wrong, meaning the way of its what's
most significant. So עילוי iluy like, you know, is מעלה, ma'alah, right,
not literally going up, but the way, the things that are the
most important parts would be brought up first. כיצד דרך עילויו? Keitzad
derech iluyo? What's the most important? הראש, Harosh, the head, which is
I guess symbolically important, not necessarily that it tastes good as meat,
והרגל, ve'haregel, then the hind leg, והחזה, ve'hechazeh, the chest, והגרה, ve'hagera,
ושתי דפנות, ve'shtei defanos, the flanks, והעוקץ, ve'ha'oketz, the tail, והרגל, ve'haregel,
and the hind leg, ושתי הידיים, ve'shtei hayadayim, and the two forearms.
Well we'll see in a minute. Anyway again there, the primarily the
structure is the same, the primary difference is where the two forearms
were, appeared in that list. So now the גמרא Gemara says, sort
of answering Michael's question, וכתיב כל נתח טוב ירך וכתף, U'chsiv kol
netach tov yareich ve'chasef, all good cut, the thigh and the shoulder.
So you see that the so here you have here in your
list, you have the רגל, regel, one of the hind legs at
the end. But here we see that the thigh is considered to
be a choice cut, so how could you have one of the
limbs, one of, you know, the thigh portion at the bottom? I
don't know, you ask me, right, it used to be that the
white meat of chicken was always the most expensive, right? But in
Israel it's like the opposite. For me also it's like the dark
meat totally tastes better. I always want the dark meat over the
white. So now it's started to shift, I don't know if you've
noticed. It's not that, you know, it's not that the white meat
I still think costs more, but the gap is not as great.
The relative cost of the dark meat has gone up. And I
think in Israel דוקא davka the dark meat costs more than the
white. So it depends on what part of the animal you're interested
in. So he says, look, the thighs here are good. How can
you tell me that the רגל regel goes at the bottom? So
the גמרא Gemara says, what?
Only meat they can have, which was sacrificed.
Right, yeah, exactly, well for the כהנים, Kohanim, but not the only,
but certainly it was a major source. The גמרא Gemara says ההיא
בכחושה. Hahi be'chshusha.
No, that is, the thigh is good if the animal is thin.
So maybe that's why, I don't know, the other, the breast area,
the chest area isn't as juicy, so then the thigh is good.
But if the animal is a fatty animal, the thigh is not
as good, and that's why we would have the leg at the
end.
Wait, are we talking specifically now about a weak animal?
No, no, no. That's the פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, not about
the קרבנות. korbanos. That's what I'm saying.
In יחזקאל... Yechezkel...
alright, okay. אמר רבא בין תנא דידן ובין רבי יוסי בתר עילויה
דבשרא אזלינן. Amar Rava bein Tanna didan u'vein Rabbi Yose basar iluya
de'bisra azlinan.
So
he says, whether our תנא, Tanna, because the list in our משנה,
Mishna, nobody exactly explained what that's based on, or רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yose list, both of them agree that the order is what are
the choice pieces of meat. So why is there a difference in
the list? I mean, we can compare the list, right? Our משנה
Mishna says, what does our משנה Mishna say? הראש והרגל ושתי ידים.
Harosh ve'haregel ve'shtei yadayim. What does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose say? הראש
והרגל. Harosh ve'haregel. Oh,
so again, it's where the ושתי ידים ve'shtei yadayim appear. So our
משנה Mishna has the ושתי ידים ve'shtei yadayim much more in the
front. He has it much more in the back. So רבא Rava
says they both agree that you go by the quality of the
cut. So what are they arguing about? מר אזיל בתר איברא דבשרא
ומר אזיל בתר שמנא דבשרא. Mar azil basar eivra de'bisra u'mar azil
basar shamna de'bisra.
One is going in terms of the, you know, the, what do
you call it? The size? Exactly, the size of the cut. So
therefore, the forelegs are a very small cut. So he puts the
forelegs at the end of the list. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose goes
according to like the, oh no, did I say that right? רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose has the forelegs at the end. Okay, I take
it back. So our תנא Tanna has the forelegs closer to the
beginning. Right, closer to the beginning. Something's... okay. So our תנא Tanna
says that you go by the size and apparently, what do I
know about animals? Apparently, the forelegs are a nice size of a
cut. So therefore our תנא Tanna has the forelegs near the front.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose goes בתר שמנא דבשרא, basar shamna de'bisra, the
fattiness, the juiciness, the quality of the cut. So the quality of
the cut, he puts the forelegs at the bottom. Okay, so that's
the end of the various lists. Now again, what do I know
about animals and so on? And I don't know if people, you
see, I saved you from making a chart of exactly comparing the
exact, although a major difference among these is where the forelegs appear
amongst the different lists. But I would say to just stop a
minute and conceptually think about these differences, it's quite fascinating in terms
of, you know, if you're going to make a choice about what
order, there's some symbolism, there's some significance in what, in why you're
making that choice. The last idea here is perhaps the most obvious
and of what we would say. You're going to bring something up
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So it's like, you know, it's, you want
to bring like your choice things up to God. So the order
you want to prioritize is what's considered a choice cut. Now whether
you define a choice by size or by quality, I mean God
isn't eating it anyway. So okay, that's a somewhat I think of
an arbitrary
decision, but nevertheless conceptually to say the choice pieces of meat go
first, that makes a lot of sense. The other opinions I think
are a little bit more unusual and therefore interesting. The way it
would walk. Why would you bring it up the way it would
walk? Is that some type of a sense that you're sort of
trying to see it as though the animal itself is bringing itself
up to the מזבח? Mizbeach? What's the significance of seeing the animal
walking itself up to the מזבח? Mizbeach? A willing sacrifice, I mean
it's focusing on you the owner bringing the animal, maybe has to
do with the sensitivity to this issue of the animal life and
seeing the
animal walk, re-serve, enact the animal's walking to the altar? I don't
exactly know. It seems like Dov wants to say something about that.
Yes? In other words, the more you approach a description that's based
on as you say the choicest cut,
the more mutilated the animal.
Oh, you just mean the more
it's just like pieces of meat. Exactly. Oh I see. So your
idea of mimicking the way it walks is in order to conceptualize
it as an animal and not as just pieces of meat. Oh,
that's a very nice idea. שקויעח. Shkoyach.
I see. שקויעח. Shkoyach. So we keep the concept of the animal,
it's very nice. שקויעח! Shkoyach! Well you're bringing an animal, you don't
want to just think like let me just bring a lot of
hamburger meat on the מזבח, Mizbeach, right? No, the whole idea is
a living thing and the life of the animal, bringing an animal.
I think it makes a lot of sense.
I talked to my second graders when we were talking about food,
where do carrots come from? They come from these cellophane wrappers in
the store.
Right. Where do eggs come from? Right, exactly. So the other two
is I doubt the other two about the way you would flay
it. The other two, the way you would flay it, that seems
to be again, or the way you would chop it up and
dismember it, that seems to just be more technical. Like once you
had to start a process one way because just the way the
animal is, it has to be flayed in a certain way, technically
it has to be cut in a certain way, then you just
continue that in terms of just the process that you began. But
I think the first position and the last one are the most
interesting about mimicking the way it would move and focusing on it
as like the choice cut. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. מאי טעמא סלקא רגלא בהדי רישא? Mai ta'ama salka regla bahadi
reisha? Now, why does the arm go together with the head?
רגלא בהדי רישא. Regla bahadi reisha. If we're going
in terms of the quality of the cut, so the גמרא Gemara
says משום דרישא נפישי בה טרמיות קריב רגלא בהדיה. Mishum derisha nefishei
bei tarmayot kariv regla bahadei. Because there are so many bones in
the head, so you bring the foot with it. Presumably means that
the head has very little meat on it. So therefore you want
to bring if you're focusing on the choice cut, you're first going
to bring the head first. Now why the head first we're going
to discuss in a minute, but the basic point is the head
isn't the choicest cut. Who wants to eat the head? Right? So
once you're bringing the head first, you want to bring a nice
big big thing with a lot of meat on it together, so
you bring the leg together with it. So now the גמרא Gemara
asks that question: דכולי עלמא מיהת ראש קרב ברישא. Dechulei alma mihat
rosh karev bereisha. Everybody seems to agree the head is brought first,
even if it's focused on choice cuts. So why is that? מנלן?
Menalan? Where is that from? דתניא, Detanya, it's taught in a ברייתא:
Braita: מנין לראש ופדר שקדמו לכל האיברים? Menayin l'rosh upader shekadmu l'chol
ha'evarim? How do you know the head and the fat come before
the other limbs? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: את ראשו ואת פדרו וערך.
Et rosho v'et pidro v'arach. It says by it says its head
and its fat and you shall place it on the fire. So
the juxtaposition shows that you place the head and the fat first
on the fire. By the way, I should remind you we're not
placing things on the fire here. We're putting them on the כבש.
Kevesh. The only next stage is then you're going to bring them
from the כבש Kevesh to the top of the מזבח Mizbeach and
presumably you're going to follow the same order. Okay, but nevertheless since
it talks about the head being first on the fire, we're talking
that's the first that's going to be brought to the כבש Kevesh
together with the פדר Peder that comes together with the head.
ואידך. V'idach. פדר אחרינא למה אתא? Peder achreina l'mah ata? How about
when it says פדר Peder again? Because the next פסוק Pasuk says
את הנתחים את הראש ואת הפדר. Et hanetachim et harosh v'et hapader.
So it repeats that again, the fat. So לכדתניא, Lechedtanya, like we
taught in the ברייתא: Braita: כיצד היה עושה? Keitzad haya oseh? Meaning
it says twice, את ראשו ואת פדרו, Et rosho v'et pidro, את
הראש ואת הפדר. Et harosh v'et hapader. So once is to tell
you you bring the head first together with the fat. What's the
next time? So the next time is to tell you why is
it repeat again את ראשו ואת פדרו? Et rosho v'et pidro?
את הנתחים, Et hanetachim, that they're placed first.
Well again they're focusing just on the juxtaposition, not on the literal
order of the פסוקים. Pesukim. So לכדתניא, Lechedtanya, like we taught in
the ברייתא: Braita: כיצד היה עושה? Keitzad haya oseh? How would you
bring it? נותן את הפדר על בית השחיטה. Notein et hapader al
beit hashchita. You would take the fat and you'd have it surround
the actual area of the cut of where the animal was slaughtered
ומעלהו, Uma'alehu, and then you put it up on the מזבח Mizbeach
like that. וזהו דרך כבוד של מעלה. V'zehu derech kavod shel ma'ala.
That's respectful to God. rather than seeing like a literally a dismembered
head with the cut neck is not does not look so nice
again. It's a little too graphic about thinking about where it came
from. So you wrap the sort of place of the severing with
the fat and then it just looks like a nice little dish
there, you know, with the trim. The fat is the trim.
So He also commanded us to הוד והדר hod v'hadar is an
idea of aesthetic. So it's interesting, the inner organs come at the
end. You might remember they were part of the list. But the
fat that's not the inner organs, that's taken and that's put around
the head and particularly around the neck, and then that's all brought
up first, and that again is even if it's not the choice
cut, symbolically, especially going back to Dov's point about, you know, thinking
about it as an animal and as a living being, you know,
that is the thing that is offered first. Rivka, yes.
And how exactly is this supposed to... by hiding the...
the fact that you slaughtered it?
The fact that you slaughtered it? Exactly those places? What... yeah. So
what's the point of hiding the
slaughtering? No, but what is the...
there's an aesthetics, I mean if you think about the whole thing...
for... well first of all there are the people that are in
the עזרה, Azara, both the כהנים Kohanim and the ישראל. Yisrael. What,
they don't see the כהן Kohen going way up to the מזבח
Mizbeach or whatever?
But you see the
head and the blood and all... oh well that's true I guess.
Unless they have opera glasses maybe.
Look, I mean I think it's a general question. The whole מזבח
Mizbeach is about, the whole מקדש Mikdash is about aesthetics, right? Why
all the gold? Why the garments? Why this? So there's a whole
way in which we as human beings, you know, in terms of
the way we sort of, it impacts our service of God, you
know, the type of aesthetics that we create, you know, I think
it's not about God but it's us and our service of God.
So if it felt like, oh well you know, these bloody things
that we're putting on the altar, I think that that
that it it sort of it it brings a sense of gore
and
violence.
But you're trying to cover that up and pretend it's not there
and make it pretty and
gold and cold blood.
Right. Look, I think it's a good... Look, first of all, we
do that every single day when we as Dov was saying, when
we go and buy our nice clean meat and I go to
the supermarket and I buy these thin-cut, you know, chicken breast, all
I have to do is put on
breadcrumbs, right? Completely removed. It could have come out of a factory.
It's a total, it's completely removed from anything living, right? So we
do that for ourselves to create a a manageable aesthetic experience. I
think you make a good point. On the one hand you definitely
have the idea of the blood כי הדם הוא הנפש ki hadam
hu hanefesh and the lifeblood is so powerful in terms of what
this ritual is about. But on the other hand, I think there's
a balancing about how do you take that power and also not
make it feel like gory and barbaric and something that completely demeans
what it it is as a religious experience. So I think we're
trying to strike that balance. But I mean, so I think you
make a good point, but I think that that's, I think there's,
you know, the power of the blood and then there's the power
of it as a religious experience that feels an elevated experience. So
the question is how to balance those. All right, so let's take
a look now at the next משנה. Mishna. הפייס השלישי, HaPayis HaShlishi,
the third lottery. Okay, there were four lotteries. So the second one
was basically bringing the... slaughtering it and bringing it up to the
altar and a few related things about cleaning the inner altar. The
third lottery: חדשים לקטורת, Chadashim l'ketoret, anybody new who has not yet
had a chance to offer up the incense, בואו והפיסו, bo'u v'hapisu,
they would announce, come and be part of the lottery.
Would they do this again in the evening?
The גמרא Gemara will discuss it. Okay. והרביעי, Ve'harevii, the fourth lottery,
חדשים עם ישנים, chadashim im yeshanim, whether you're new or old, whether
you've done this before or not, everybody, the fourth lottery is again
open to all the כהנים. Kohanim. מי מעלה איבר מן הכבש למזבח,
Mi ma'aleh evar min hakevesh lamizbeach, who would bring the limbs from
the ramp up to the altar and actually put them on the
altar itself? Now I should say something by the way, I would
have assumed here that this last lottery is similar to the second
one. One person, they stop at one person and then they get
the next, you know, 13 guys to come along and to finish
it up. Okay. So that's going to be... we'll see in a
later משנה Mishna about that, about how many guys were involved in
the final stage of bringing it up, or not in the next...
the later משנה Mishna is going to talk about the afternoon מנחה.
Mincha. But anyway, the משנה Mishna here is not clear how many
כהנים Kohanim would bring it from the ramp to the top of
the מזבח, Mizbeach, and there's a later רש"י Rashi that seems to
indicate that it would only be one כהן, Kohen, which is very
bizarre, like you have nine כהנים Kohanim bringing it to the ramp,
then you go ahead and you do the קטורת, ketoret, then you
send one כהן Kohen up the ramp to run up and down
and to bring it all up. Okay. But it doesn't tell you
how many כהנים Kohanim did the second part of from the ramp
to the top, and a later רש"י Rashi indicates it was only
one. Yes, Dov.
So I just wanted... what do you think about this? It seems
to me like it's
getting into... Sure, we didn't
mention, we didn't even
mention the flaying and the dismembering.
Right, besides on the ramp, they put the pieces on the ramp.
So some כהן Kohen must have had to wash it down.
Right exactly, but they would wash it down before the ramp. Oh,
wash down the ramp.
On the ramp it must have been filled with grease and blood.
Right, this is the first thing in the... anyway go on, sorry.
Okay fine, but there must have been all sorts of
activities to maintain this institution that were not... that are not being
listed. Exactly. And if you're in this building at 1:30 in the
afternoon you see guys stuffing things... Right, totally. And then you show...
first of all, first of all this is only the special פיס
Payis and we'll discuss in a minute for the afternoon תמיד Tamid
that they would do for the תמיד. Tamid. All the other קרבנות
Korbanot would be taken as they come, right? So even for the
actual הקרבה Hakrava of the קרבן, Korban, this whole idea of doing
the whole lottery was only for the sort of communal תמידים Tamidim
and the communal קטרת Ketoret and the things that are done in
the morning that are done for the ציבור Tzibbur and that are
done regularly. All the stuff that happens afterwards, even the slaughtering and
the throwing and everything, you know, whichever כהן Kohen is available comes
and does it. So that's number one. And number two, you're right,
even during these events there are many other things that are not
seen as sort of עבודות Avodot or not seen as
sort of כבודיק Kavodik type of things that aren't being mentioned. The
whole flaying and dismembering wasn't being mentioned. So you're completely correct, these
are not... this is not the total list. But let's keep on
going, okay? תנא... Tanna... we've got to keep it going. תנא מעולם
לא שנה אדם בה, Tanna me'olam lo shana adam bah, nobody ever
did the קטרת Ketoret twice. Now that wasn't like some miracle, that
was because they didn't let somebody do it twice. Okay. מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, what's the reasoning? What's the reasoning not that it worked
out that way, but what's the reasoning they didn't allow anybody? Why
did they insist only new people? So אמר רבי חנינא מפני שמעשרת,
Amar Rabi Chanina mipnei she-measheret, because it makes you rich and therefore
they wanted to give everybody a chance. So how do you know
it makes you rich? אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי מאי טעמא, Amar
leh Rav Papa le-Abaye mai ta'ama, where do you... where do you
get this from? Where do you know? What's the basis of this?
אילימא משום דכתיב ישימו קטורה באפך וכליל על מזבחך, Ileima mishum de-chtiv
Yasimu Ketorah be-apecha ve-chalil al mizbechecha, this is by, right,
וזאת הברכה, Ve-zot Haberacha, right, to לוי, Levi, but obviously here in
the context speaking to the כהנים, Kohanim, they will put the incense
God in your nostrils, they will raise up the incense, וכתיב בתריה,
u-chtiv batrei, and the next verse says, ברך ה' חילו, Barech Hashem
cheilo, God should bless his wealth. So one explanation of the word
חילו, cheilo, God should bless his strength, his wealth. So you see,
if you bring the קטרת, Ketoret, God blesses your fortune, your wealth.
אי הכי, I hachi, if that's true, why is it limited to
the קטרת? Ketoret? עולה נמי כתיב, Olah nami chtiv, by an עולה
Olah it says, וכליל על מזבחך, ve-chalil al mizbechecha, and they will...
it says ישימו קטורה באפך, Yasimu Ketorah be-apecha, they'll bring up the
incense, and the fully burnt sacrifices on your altar. So fully burnt
is the עולה. Olah. So and then right afterwards it says ברך
ה' חילו. Barech Hashem cheilo. Actually what's juxtaposed is the עולה Olah
together with the ברך ה' חילו. Barech Hashem cheilo. אמר ליה הא
שכיחא והא לא שכיחא. Amar leh hash'chicha ve-ha lo sh'chicha. No, one
is very common, the עולה Olah is very common, the קטרת Ketoret
is not very common. What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says
what it means is, look, we know that there's not... that
there's a limited number of people that are wealthy in this world.
Not everybody is rich. So therefore it would not make any sense
to think that when the פסוק Pasuk is promising this blessing of
wealth, that it refers to everybody who brings the עולה, Olah, then
every כהן Kohen would be rich, and we know that's not going
to happen and we know that's not true. So obviously the פסוק
Pasuk has to be referring to the thing that's more rare. The
תוספות ישנים א Tosafot Yeshanim Aleph offers a different explanation. He says,
yeah, fine, they both make you rich, but we didn't have to
do a lottery for the עולה. Olah. Everybody's going to get a
chance to do an עולה, Olah, right? There's tons of עולות Olot
that are brought every day. So that didn't need a lottery. Maybe
it will make you rich, but it didn't need a lottery. The
only thing that needs a lottery is the קטרת Ketoret because that's
only one... you know, only happens twice a day, there there's going
to be a lot of competition. Okay, so therefore, I mean, not
just we have the lottery, we had to limit it to new
people. Okay, there's no need to limit it to new people to
an עולה. Olah. Even if we don't limit it, even if you've
done it before, everybody's going to get a chance to bring an
עולה. Olah. I don't care if you've done it before, if you
haven't done it before, there's going to be plenty of עולות. Olot.
Not everybody's going to get a chance to do a קטרת. Ketoret.
So therefore we have the limit. So according to him, he wants
to say אין הכי נמי, In hachi nami, maybe an עולה Olah
will make you rich, but we don't have to limit the opportunity
with an עולה, Olah, maybe. Anyway, that's his answer. רש"י's Rashi answer
is just, no, not everything makes you rich. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר רבא לא משכחת צורבא מרבנן, Amar Rava
lo mishkachat tzurba merabbanan, you will not find a Torah scholar... it's
actually quite interesting because צורבא מרבנן tzurba merabbanan literally means a student
of the Rabbis, does not literally mean like somebody who's an actual
רב Rav who has סמיכה semicha and is a major authority. So
he says but you won't find the students of the Rabbis, דמורי,
de-mori, who will give פסק, psak, אלא דאתי משבט לוי, ela de-ati
mi-shevet Levi,
if he's going to give פסק psak he either derives from the
tribe of לוי, Levi, או משבט יששכר, o mi-shevet Yissachar, or from
the tribe of יששכר. Yissachar. לוי דכתיב יורו משפטיך... Levi de-chtiv Yoru
mishpatecha...
he will teach your your edicts, your laws to Jacob, so הוראה,
hora'ah, right, that's by the לוי, Levi, because before by the way
the rabbinic class emerged in the בית שני Bayis Sheni period, clearly,
right, it was the כהנים לויים kohanim levi'im, that were the rabbinic
that were the
religious authorities, both in terms of the עבודה avodah in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and in terms of the teaching of תורה, Torah,
right? The תורה Torah is always talking about the כהנים Kohanim and
the לויים Levi'im that are the ones that teach תורה, Torah, להורות
את בני ישראל בין הטמא ובין הטהור, le-horos es bnei Yisrael bein
hatameh u'vein hatahor, right? It's all
it's all about the כהנים Kohanim teaching and the- about the ritual
law, יורו משפטיך ליעקב yoru mishpatekha le-Ya'akov and so on, and that's
and sometimes the לויים. Levi'im And when then their role as תורה
Torah teachers and certainly after the חורבן בית המקדש churban Beis HaMikdash
their complete role as religious authority is put aside, but anyway, but
then the rabbinic class comes to substitute for the כהנים Kohanim and
לויים, Levi'im. in particular to take on this role of teaching תורה.
Torah. So what's Hillel, Shammai... one minute. So anyway, so we'll get
to those. So the גמרא Gemara says, so okay, יורו משפטיך ליעקב,
yoru mishpatekha le-Ya'akov, so therefore, oh, if you have a תורה Torah
scholar, so in a way this is connecting the phenomenon of like
the rabbinic class and the new sort of people who teach תורה
Torah to those to whom that was assigned who played that role
in the time of the תורה. Torah. So they either derive from
the tribe of לוי Levi who says יורו משפטיך ליעקב, yoru mishpatekha
le-Ya'akov, or יששכר. Yissaschar. דכתיב ומבני יששכר יודעי
בינה לעתים לדעת מה יעשה ישראל, dikhtiv u'mibnei Yissaschar yodei binah le-ittim
lada'as mah ya'aseh Yisrael,
and from the children of יששכר Yissaschar who know the wisdom of
times, to know what the Jewish people should do. So presumably they
have the knowledge to teach Israel. Okay, so those are- that's- that's
where they'll come from. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואימא יהודה, ve-eima
Yehuda, what about the tribe of יהודה Yehuda נמי? nami? דכתיב יהודה
מחוקקי, dikhtiv Yehuda mechokeki, יהודה Yehuda my lawgiver. So you see, I
mean, יהודה Yehuda gives law, so clearly then, you
know, that- that- that they
should פסקן pasken הלכה. halacha. So, אסוקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא קאמינא. asukei
shma'ata aliba de-hilchasa ka'amina. No, I'm talking about- this is a very
famous phrase- אסוקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא. asukei shma'ata aliba de-hilchasa. To conclude
to- to- to lift up, rise up from an- a discussion according
to the right הלכה, halacha, to emerge from the whole שקלא וטריא
shakla ve-tarya the back and forth and to come to the right
conclusion. So יהודה Yehuda might sort of give ruling, but he's not
always right. So the others it says, one minute, the others it
says, right, יורו, yoru, הוראה, hora'ah, or לדעת מה לעשות. lada'as mah
la'asos. It's not just giving edicts, they actually know what's right and
actually what they say is actually the accurate הלכה. halacha. Now, I
want to say a few things about this, besides the first thing
I said, which is an important thing to be aware of. By
the way, the נצי"ב Netziv talks about this a lot in his
introduction to the שאילתות. She'iltos. This whole idea of, you know, when
the תורה Torah talks for example about the whole פסוקים pesukim for
rabbinic authority, לא תסור ימין ושמאל, lo sasur yamin u'smol, דעשית על
פי התורה אשר יורוך, de-asisa al pi hatorah asher yoru'cha, the-
the people that the תורה Torah is talking about in the פסוקים,
pesukim, the- it says אל הכהנים הלוים ואל השופט. el hakohanim halevi'im
ve'el hashofet. So שופט shofet is singular, but כהנים Kohanim לויים, Levi'im,
those are the primary people that are giving teaching and teaching תורה
Torah and teaching הלכה, halacha, whatever, in the תורה, Torah, back it's
replaced by the rabbis, but here the גמרא Gemara is connecting it
back, also connecting it to יששכר, Yissaschar, who in like the rabbinic
mindset was, you know, completely sort of represented the forerunner of תורה
Torah sages. And then it's interesting the contrast to יהודה. Yehuda. So
I want to say a few things about this. Number one, and
the מהרש"א Maharsha already, you know, whatever,
whatever, discusses some of this, you know, יהודה Yehuda is also where
the נשיאים nesi'im come from, like רבי Rebbe comes from יהודה, Yehuda,
the whole tribe of יהודה, Yehuda, דוד המלך Dovid HaMelech comes from
יהודה, Yehuda, there are גמרות Gemaras that speak about, you know, about-
about דוד Dovid as a giving rulings and so on. So you
know, how does that fit in with the גמרא Gemara sort of
saying oh no, it's not- the- you know, they don't do really
like אסוקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא, asukei shma'ata aliba de-hilchasa, they don't have
that much authority? So first of all, it's interesting the difference between
מחוקק, mechokek, which is a lawgiver, and to give פסק. psak. It's
basically the difference between legislation and, you know, and sort of- sort
of judicial interpretation and authority. So sure, יהודה Yehuda is the- is
the kings, is דוד המלך, Dovid HaMelech, you know, it's רבי יהודה
הנשיא, Rebbe Yehuda HaNasi, it's the people that- the נשיאים nesi'im in
the- in the time of the תנאים Tannaim who had the, you
know, the descendants of רבי יהודה הנשיא Rebbe Yehuda HaNasi who had
the political slash rabbinic authority. So that's about power and authority and
maybe even legislative authority, but that's a different type of a role
than it is in terms of הוראה, hora'ah, which is sort of
dealing with the law after it's been given and determining what is
the proper application, what's the proper interpretation.
What's actual de-facto case law.
Yeah, but also one is interpretation and application and the other is
the issuing of the law and the legislature. Okay, so anyway, that's
one difference between the word מחוקק mechokek and also in practice, יהודה
Yehuda representing מלכות malchus and רבי יהודה הנשיא Rebbe Yehuda HaNasi and
that sort of issue of political slash religious authority. The other important
thing is that I think it's important to focus on the original
part of the statement which it says צורבא מרבנן tzurba merabbanan We're
not coming and saying if you look at all of the תנאים
*Tannaim* and all of the great Rabbis, the only ones who ever
came up with the right הלכה halacha *Halacha*, סוגיא דשמעתתא אליבא דהלכתא
*Sugya d'shma'teta aliba d'hilchisa*, were from יששכר *Issachar* or לוי *Levi*. That's
crazy, right? Really, were we to look at all the major authorities
in ש"ס Shas *Shas*, they would all be either from יששכר *Issachar*
or לוי *Levi*? No. If you sort of, if you can reach
that level, you'll make minor exceptions and you can reach that level.
But if you're a צורבא מרבנן *Tzurba m'rabbanan*, if you're only a
student and you're already פסקן *paskening* correctly, then it must come from
the genes. Okay, exactly, then it's coming, then you're from, then it's
because you got this יחוס *yichus* and then, oh, you must be
from לוי *Levi* or you must be from יששכר *Issachar*, you're still
just a צורבא מרבנן *Tzurba m'rabbanan* and you're still פסקן *paskening* פסקן
*paskening* correctly. And that's what I think is often missed in this
passage, that it's not about if there's a sage, but if there's
a צורבא מרבנן *Tzurba m'rabbanan*. You know, sages they can be wherever
they're from. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* comes and continues.
So that was an interesting little digression from the blessing of לוי
*Levi*. So, אמר רב יוחנן *Amar Rav Yochanan*, says רב יוחנן *Rav
Yochanan*, אמר רב יוחנן *Amar Rav Yochanan*, אין מפיסין על תמיד Tamid.
שבין הערבים *Ein mafisin al tamid she'bein ha'arbayim*. Now, I think Michael
asked this, what happens to the afternoon תמיד tamid, *tamid*? Right, you
know, you have to also bring a חביתין *chavitin* and קטורת k'tores,
*ketores* and you have the whole afternoon תמיד Tamid, *tamid*, almost all
the same stuff. Who does that lottery? So, אין מפיסין על תמיד
tamid שבין הערבים *Ein mafisin al tamid she'bein ha'arbayim*, you don't do
another lottery. אלא כהן Kohen שזכה בו בשחרית זכה בו בערבית *Ella
kohen she'zachah bo bashacharis zachah bo ba'arvis*. You get double duty. Anybody
who got the morning קרבן korban. *korban* gets to do the same
job in the afternoon. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מתיבי *Mesivei*,
I'll ask you on this. כשם שמפיסין בשחרית כך מפיסין בין הערבים
Bein ha'arbayim, *Keshem she'mafisin bashacharis kach mafisin bein ha'arbayim*. We have a
ברייתא Baraisa *braisa* that says the same way you do a lottery
in the morning, you do it in the afternoon. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, שאני היא בקטורת *Shani hi b'ketores*. No, that's not
talking about the תמיד Tamid *tamid*, that's talking about the third lottery
was repeated, the קטורת k'tores. *ketores* was done, was done again in
the afternoon because again, you want to give everybody a chance. והתניא
*Ve'hatanya*, wait a minute, we have a ברייתא Braita *braisa* that says,
כשם שמפיסין לו בשחרית כך מפיסין לו בערבית *Keshem she'mafisin lo bashacharis
kach mafisin lo ba'arvis*, the same way you do it for it
in the morning, you do a lottery for it in the afternoon,
but לו *lo* is masculine, קטורת k'tores? *ketores* is feminine, so it
works if it's referring to the תמיד tamid *tamid*, it does not
work if it's referring to the קטורת k'tores *ketores*. אימה לה *Eima
lah*. All right, switch the גרסא *girsa* to say לה *lah* feminine.
והתניא *Ve'hatanya*, wait a minute, but we have a ברייתא *braisa* that
says, כשם שמפיסין לו בשחרית כך מפיסין לו בערבית *Keshem she'mafisin lo
bashacharis kach mafisin lo ba'arvis*, the same way you do a lottery
in the morning for it masculine, you do it for it masculine
in the afternoon. וכשם שמפיסין לה בשחרית כך מפיסין לה בערבית *Vekeshem
she'mafisin lah bashacharis kach mafisin lah ba'arvis*, and the same way you
do for it feminine, you do for it feminine in the afternoon.
So you repeat two lotteries, one for something masculine, i.e., the תמיד
tamid. *tamid*, and one for something feminine, the קטורת k'tores. *ketores*. So
you see that they did the תמיד tamid. *tamid* a second lottery.
So אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק *Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav
Yitzchak*, הכא בשבת עסקינן הואיל ומשמרות מתחדשות *Hacha b'Shabbos askinan hoil umishmaros
mitchadshos*. So that was a cool answer to pull from your hat.
We're talking about שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* because on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* a
different shift is working in the afternoon than the morning, right, because
they switch. The one goes out and the other comes in and
they switch after the morning תמיד tamid, *tamid*. So that's why, because
there's a new shift on. But when there's not a new shift,
it's the same people in the morning that are in the afternoon.
Because you've got this new shift that comes in for the week?
For the week.
So שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* is the transition of the two weeks.
Right, שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos* is the day, it's like reading the תורה Torah *Torah* at
מנחה
*Mincha* at שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. Right, well they did it when they
did the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim. *Lechem Hapanim*, that's the new group,
the new group put on the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim, *Lechem Hapanim*,
the old group took it off, and that was the shift and
that was the switching. Right, so here he says that was for
everything?
What? On שבת *Shabbos*?
On שבת *Shabbos* for all the stuff that was in the afternoon
they'd have to do it again. But if it's not שבת *Shabbos*,
then everybody who does stuff in the morning does in the afternoon,
certainly for the תמיד tamid. *tamid*, maybe even for the קטורת k'tores
*ketores*. So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says, ולמאי דסלקא דעתך מעיקרא *U'lemai
d'salka daitan me'ikara*, נפישי להו פייסות *Nafishi lehu paisos*.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says one minute, we got a problem.
Because you have now beautifully explained that all this, these ברייתא *braisos*
about repeating, are all talking about שבת *Shabbos* when there's a new
shift. But we for a while were seriously considering the possibility that
every day there would be a new lottery in the afternoon for
the קטורת k'tores. *ketores*, for the תמיד tamid, *tamid*. So one minute,
but we said that there were four פייסות *paisos*. Now you're going
to have five or six, right, if you're going to repeat some
things in the afternoon? So aren't you going to have too many
lotteries? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מייתי כולהו מצפרא *Maiti kulehu
mitzafra*. No, no, no, you did the lottery in the morning. אצפרא
עשו
*Atzafra asu*. They came in the morning. דזכי בשחרית זכי דזכי בערבית
זכי *De'zachi beshachris zachi de'zachi ba'arvis zachi*. So basically everybody got together
in the morning and the only thing is that in the morning
you distributed. You fourteen guys or thirteen guys or whatever, you guys
are going to do the תמיד tamid, *tamid* now, the next thirteen
guys you'll be doing the תמיד tamid, *tamid* in the afternoon. You
win the קטורת k'tores, *ketores* now, the guy next to you is
going to do the קטורת *ketores* in the afternoon. So not literally
that we actually did a new lottery, but we assigned them. two
different people in the afternoon based but it was
he's saying that's the הוה אמינא.
hava amina Okay. In the מסקנא maskana we're saying there was no
second lottery. Everything that was in the morning was repeated in the
afternoon, the only time you did a second lottery was on שבת
when it was משמר. mishmar. But in the הוה אמינא hava amina.
that it was a different lottery, it was different people. In the
end, the גמרא Gemara in order to make it only a certain
number of lotteries can't have a real different lottery. So that's fine.
It was all the same lottery but it was assigned. The afternoon
people, different afternoon people were assigned at that time. Okay, the first
thirteen guys were assigned the morning and the next thirteen guys were
assigned the afternoon. It was different people but it was not a
actual different lottery. Okay, so now the but that was the הוה
אמינא. In the end we seem to be rejecting that and saying
that it was just the same people in the morning did it
in the afternoon. Okay, הרביעי, harevii, the fourth lottery, חדשים עם ישנים,
chadashim im yeshanim, new and old people, everybody came to do the
lottery again in order to bring it from the ramp to the
altar.
מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Masnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
Our משנה Mishnah is not like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a משנה Mishnah תמיד. tamid.
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר המעלה איברים לכבש הוא מעלה אותם למזבח.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer: hamaleh evarim l'kevesh hu maaleh osam l'mizbeach.
The one that brought it to the ramp, he'd be the same
one that would bring it up to the to the top. Of
course it makes sense. So במאי קמיפלגי? Bimai kamifligi? What's this debate
whether you should have the same guy who brings it to the
ramp bring it to the top or get new guys? So מר
סבר ברוב עם הדרת מלך. Mar savar birov am hadras melech. The
more people that are involved the better, it's glory to the King,
it shows everybody wants to have a piece of it, there are
all these different כהנים Kohanim running around and different people doing it.
ומר סבר במקום שכינה לאו אורח ארעא. Umar savar bimkom Shechinah lav
orech araa. It's not respectful to the to the שכינה. Shechinah. Basically...
I'm sorry... במקום שכינה לאו אורח ארעא. Bimkom Shechinah lav orech araa.
In the place of God's presence, that's not respectful. What's not respectful?
So רש"י Rashi says it's not respectful basically like, okay, I'm done,
I'm leaving my stuff here, let's get somebody else to finish it
up. Meaning it doesn't look necessarily that more people are doing it
because it's all a way of, you know, honoring sort of the
service, maybe it's like I don't want to, you know, I'll get
somebody else to clean up after me, I'll get somebody else to
finish for me. So therefore it's more important that you should go
back and do it rather than make it seem like you're just
dumping this on somebody to finish up.
דטריח ליה מילתא. D'terich leh milsa.
Right. רש"י Rashi says דטריח ליה מילתא. D'terich leh milsa. Okay. So
alright. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: לא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב איתא דרבי
יהודה ולא דרבי יהודה איתא דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Lo d'Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov aisa d'Rabbi Yehuda v'lo d'Rabbi Yehuda aisa d'Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov doesn't hold of
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't hold of
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. דאם כן בטלו להו
פייסות. D'im ken batlu lehu piyasos. Because then you won't have enough
enough lotteries. I assume that doesn't need any explanation, right? No. So
anyway, so what it means is that רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov said that there was not a that there was
not a separate lottery for the guy to bring it up the
ramp. The same guy brought it from the ramp and then who
brought it and then brought it from the ramp to the top.
So according to him you only had three lotteries. Where does he
get a fourth? So the way you could get the fourth lottery
is based on an earlier discussion about רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, about
whether there would be a lottery for the guy, we know there
was a lottery for the guy who burnt the קטורת, who brought
the קטורת. What about the guy who brought the fire pan, you
know, the shovel the coals for the קטורת? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said that was just the guy standing next to the קטורת guy.
But you could say there was a separate lottery. So basically what
the גמרא is saying is according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov you didn't have a lottery for bringing the limbs
from the altar to the top of the ramp because it was
the same guy, but you would have had your fourth lottery in
terms of the guy who would shovel the coals for the קטורת.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says there would not be a
lottery for the guy who would shovel the coals, it would just
be the guy standing next to him, he would obviously say like
our משנה Mishnah that there would be a lottery for bringing it
from the ramp to the top. ואי משכחת תנא דתני חמש, V'ei
meshkachas tanna d'sani chamesh,
and if you can ever find an author of a ברייתא that
has five lotteries, where would the five lottery come
from? דלא כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב ודלא כרבי יהודה. D'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov v'd'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda. It would have to reject both of
those. It would have to say (A) it would not be the
same guy who would bring it from the ramp to the top,
that would be a separate lottery, that gets you four. (B) it
would not be the guy standing next to the קטורת person who
would do the coals, that would be a separate lottery, and that
would get you five. Okay.
What do you mean ואי משכחת תנא דתני חמש? V'ei meshkachas tanna
d'sani chamesh? I could say that I could double the size of
the ש"ס by adding that...
he's not asking, he's just saying there's a theoretical possibility out there
based on the different ideas we've heard, there are two things being
debated. There's also a theoretical possibility of three, but the גמרא assumes
that nobody would say less than four. Four is like a solid
number, right? There are three things that everybody agrees on, right, which
is the תרומת הדשן, terumas hadeshen, the תמיד, tamid, and the קטורת.
And then there are two that are debated. Number one is the
מחתה, machta, the fire pan for the קטורת, was that done? And
number two is bringing it from the ramp to the top, was
that a lottery or was that the same guy? So if there
are those three and two debated, you have the possibility of three,
you have the possibility of five, and you have the possibility of
four. So we know two versions of four. The גמרא's rejecting the
possibility of five, just saying in theory there's a possibility of
five. Okay. Alright. תמיד, Tamid? so that's the morning and that's the
okay now we get to the afternoon which we've already seen is
a question whether they would have a. whether they would sort of
have the same guys do the afternoon or whether it would be
different but maybe determined at the same lottery. So let's take a
look of how the תמיד Tamid. was brought. תמיד Tamid? קרב karav
בתשעה be'tishah בעשרה be'asarah באחד עשר be'achad asar בשנים עשר be'shneim asar
לא פחות ולא יותר. lo pachut ve'lo yoter. The תמיד tamid, would
be brought, meaning from the time of the bringing of the limbs
with meaning the bringing to the altar, nine, ten, eleven, or twelve
people, no fewer and no greater. Now again, our earlier משנה mishnah
spoke about thirteen, but that wasn't limiting itself to the limbs. That
spoke about slaughtering, throwing the blood, the bringing up of the סלת,
solet, the bringing up of the יין, yayin, but if you counted
the actual bringing of the limbs, it was nine. So the standard
bringing of the limbs is nine, but it can get to be
as much as twelve. How is that possible? Okay. כיצד? Keitzad? עצמו
בתשעה. Atzmo be'tishah. Limbs of the animal itself were nine. ובחג U've'chag
ביד
אחד צלוחית של מים. be'yad echad tzeluchit shel mayim. On סוכות, Sukkot,
they would bring a pitcher of water for the ניסוך המים nisuch
hamayim that would be done with the תמיד. tamid, Okay, with the
morning תמיד. So again, that wasn't the limbs, but it was things
being brought to the altar. הרי כאן עשרה. Harei kan asarah. That's
ten. בין הערבים, in the afternoon, באחד עשר, be'achad asar, there'd be
eleven. ובגוף עצמו בתשעה, U've'guf atzmo be'tishah, the base nine, ושנים בידם
שני גזירי עצים, u'shnayim be'yadam shenei gizirei etzim, and two people would
be bringing two logs of to put on the fire. They would
put the logs on the fire. Now, תוספות Tosafot points out they
would also put logs on the fire in the morning, but that
was done with the person who did the תרומת הדשן. terumat hadeshen.
Okay. He did the logs on the fire in the morning.
So they didn't need any more noted
or I don't know, but the logs in the afternoon, that was
done at the time of the תמיד, so that would get you
up to eleven. ובשבת
באחד עשר, U've'shabbat be'achad asar, it would also be up to eleven
on שבת. How is that? הוא עצמו בתשעה, Hu atzmo be'tishah, it
itself at nine, ושנים בידם שני בזיכי לבונה, u'shnayim be'yadam shenei bezichei
levonah, and two of them were carrying the two sort of cups
of the incense to burn from the לחם הפנים.
lechem hapanim של לחם הפנים, Shel
lechem hapanim, that was in the morning. Right? Or otherwise you'd get
thirteen, right? So again, that's in the morning. So the two extra
logs in the afternoon can't get added to this. This is in
the morning. So how do you get twelve? Twelve is ובשבת שבתוך
החג, u've'shabbat she'betoch ha'chag, שבת on סוכות. Sukkot. Because then you have
the two things that are done in the morning. ביד
אחד צלוחית של מים. Be'yad echad tzeluchit shel mayim. The two things
that are done with with the afternoon sacrifice, the extra things that
are done are the two logs, and that would be everything on
the morning sacrifice. You would you could get extra things done, either
the water on סוכות Sukkot or the incense, the two guys carrying
the two things of incense on שבת. So when those happens together,
שבת סוכות, Shabbat Sukkot, you'd get three extra which would bring you
up to twelve. And that's how you'd get twelve.
Wasn't the קטרת ketoret every day? No.
Oh yes, but that was that was the קטרת, ketoret, that was
a separate thing. That wasn't together with the תמיד. That was the
קטרת פנימית. ketoret penimit.
This one
is the לבונה levonah of the לחם הפנים, not the daily incense.
Right. Now, it is worth pointing out by the way, again, the
disproportionate way some of these jobs are assigned. Either two people to
two little things of לבונה. levonah. I gotta carry this one little
thing of לבונה, levonah, you get to carry the head and the
hind leg. Okay. So, as I say, which things they decided to
split up, like okay you carry the סלת, solet, you carry the
יין, yayin, but the big you get carry two flanks of the
animal, right? So it's a little bit wild how they would divide
some of that up. The other thing worth mentioning though is is
that in this list of things that were with the תמיד, what's
shockingly absent is not conceptually being bundled together is the earlier משנה
mishnah which tells you the what do you call it? The מנחת
נסכים, minchat nesachim, the wine and the flour that came with every
קרבן. Korban And that came with the תמיד, and that was in
the list. So if you're gonna talk about the incidental things like
the ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim and the קטרת ketoret that relates to
the שולחן shulchan in terms of how things that were brought together
with the תמיד, it seems to me bizarre that you're not talking
about the flour and the wine that came together with it as
well. The wine was poured at the base? No, at the top!
Right on top of the יסוד! yesod! I don't so I don't
get it. I don't get it. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. אמר רב אבא Amar Rav Abba ואי תימא ve'i teima
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama ואי תימא ve'i teima רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. אין מנסכין מים בחג אלא בתמיד של שחר. Ein menaschin
mayim be'chag ela be'tamid shel shachar. You only can do the water
pouring libation on סוכות Sukkot with the morning תמיד. Okay, because that's
clear in our משנה. mishnah. It only bundled it together with the
morning. ממה Mimma מדקתני mide'katani ובשבת שבתוך החג ביד אחד צלוחית של
מים. u've'shabbat she'betoch ha'chag be'yad echad tzeluchit shel mayim. Since it says
that you add one guy to bring stuff to the altar on
you get to your number of twelve by שבת, two for the
incense of the לחם הפנים and one for the water. And plus
the nine gets you twelve. ואי סלקא דעתך Ve'i salka daitach בתמיד
שבין הערבים be'tamid she'bein ha'arbayim מנסכין, menaschin,
if you think it's possible to do the ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim
on סוכות Sukkot in the afternoon תמיד, בכל נמי משכחת לה. be'chol
nami mashkachat lah. I can easily—why do you have to give a
special case of שבת סוכות? Shabbat Sukkot? Any weekday סוכות Sukkot you'll
get twelve. Why? You'll get the normal nine, right, in the afternoon,
plus the two logs gets you eleven, plus the ניסוך המים nisuch
hamayim gets you twelve. So it's so easy to get twelve, you
know, if you can do it in the afternoon. afternoon. And we
didn't give that scenario. So therefore, clearly you cannot do it in
the afternoon. Okay, so גמרא says, אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tanyina, we also taught in
a משנה Mishnah that supports this idea that the ניסוך המים nisuch
hamayim was only in the in the with the morning sacrifice. ולמנסך
אומר לו, U'limnaseiach omer lo,
and the guy came to do the pouring of the water, they
said to him, the people in the עזרה, Azarah, הגבה ידך, hagbei
yadecha,
lift up your hands. We want to see you pouring the water.
There was basically a funnel in the corner of the מזבח mizbe'ach
where they would pour the water and the wine and it would
go down and it would go into the cavity underneath the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Right, oh I'm sorry. I wasn't I thought you just
meant I thought you asked would it be at the base. It
wasn't at the base. They went to the top, they would pour
the wine down through a funnel that would a pipe that would
go into a cavity. So when they came to do the pouring
of the water, they said, lift up your hands, let's see you
do the pouring. Now why was that so important? Not just they
wanted to witness a ritual, but for the following reason: שפעם אחת,
Shepa'am achat, because it never says anywhere in the תורה that you
did a libation of water on the altar. Obviously סוכות Sukkos is
associated with water, but it never speaks about this עבודה. avoda. And
it's all a מסורה mesora that the פרושים Perushim had, but the
צדוקים Tzedukim completely rejected the idea of water libations on סוכות. Sukkos.
And this, here's what happened. שפעם אחת ניסך על גבי רגליו. Shepa'am
achat nisach al gabei raglav. One time the guy was a צדוקי,
Tzeduki, which was very prevalent among the כהנים, Kohanim, and he and
you know, maybe by pressure he had to go up there with
the water, but he wasn't going to go through with the ritual.
So he just spilled it on his legs, on his feet. Figured
nobody could see him, he's up at the top of the altar,
so he didn't pour it into the actual funnel, he poured it
on his feet. Also to show disdain probably. ורגמוהו כל העם באתרוגיהם,
Urgamuhu kol ha'am be'esrogayhem, and they all stoned him with their אתרוגים.
esrogim. They were all had their לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so they all stoned him with their
אתרוג. esrog. שמע מינה. Shema mina. So that's a good proof, that's
a good proof that it's in the morning. Now how's it a
proof that it's in the morning? Because they're having the לולב lulav
and אתרוג, esrog, because that's in the morning. Of course, maybe it
just happened to be that way. Maybe it doesn't have to be
in the morning. Maybe by chance it was in the morning. So
רש"י Rashi says, if it was just by chance, it wouldn't have
mentioned the אתרוג. esrog. If it's mentioning the אתרוג, esrog, it's mentioning
them to underscore that it had to be in the morning. Personally,
I don't know. I will bet you you will not forget the
scene of the כהן Kohen being stoned by the אתרוגים. esrogim. Okay,
so I think that it was valuable to point out the אתרוגים
esrogim even if not to teach a הלכה that the ניסוך המים
nisuch hamayim has to be in the morning. Yes, Charlie?
Thanks, thanks to Josephus as saying that this צדוקי Tzeduki was actually
Alexander Jannai, who was got so upset that he set his goons
on the people and a lot of people died.
Oh my gosh. Okay, that's fascinating.
You're degenerating, cause you have a pun here of מי רגלי. mei
raglai.
Yeah,
I was wondering about that too, that's a good point. Thank you.
Okay, so שמע מינה. shema mina. תניא, Tanya, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
אומר. Rabi Shimon bar Yochai omer. מנין לתמיד של בין הערבים Minayin
letamid shel bein ha'arbayim שטעון sheta'un שני גזירי עצים? shnei gezeirei eitzim?
Now how do you know you bring two logs with the additional
logs with the afternoon תמיד? ושני כהנים, V'shnei Kohanim, and not only
that, you need two כהנים? Kohanim? שנאמר Shene'emar says, וערכו עצים. v'archu
eitzim. וערכו עצים, v'archu eitzim, it speaks about when you bring the
קרבן it says they should arrange the logs. So maybe that means
the morning logs? מנו לתמיד של שחר, Minu letamid shel shachar, but
we know that's not required in that's not you don't have to
tell me that in the morning תמיד. דכתיב Dichsiv it already says,
ובער עליה הכהן עצים בבקר בבקר וערך עליה. u'bi'er aleha hakohen eitzim
baboker baboker v'arach aleha.
So it already says that he arranges the wood every morning. So
why does it say again וערכו? v'archu? So תנהו ענין לתמיד של
בין הערבים, tana'ahu inyan letamid shel bein ha'arbayim, tell me the afternoon.
And because it's וערכו v'archu in the plural, so there I'm going
to learn out that there are going to be two כהנים Kohanim
involved. So I learn out two things: it's redundant, so you do
it in the afternoon, and it's in plural, so you do it
with two כהנים. Kohanim. ואימא אידי ואידי בתמיד של שחר, V'eima ai
d'ai b'tamid shel shachar, maybe both of them are the morning תמיד?
ורחמנא אמר עביד, v'Rachmana amar avid, first have one כהן Kohen do
it, והדר עביד, v'hadar avid, and then do it again? Maybe do
it twice, two placings of wood in the morning. No, אם כן
נימא קרא ובער ובער. im kein nima kra u'bi'er u'bi'er. No, then
it wouldn't have used a different word וערכו. v'archu. It would be
basically telling you do the same thing twice, it would have used
the same
verb, burn it, burn it. איכא דרחמנא ובער, Ika d'Rachmana u'bi'er, no,
it could have said that. Had it said that, הוה אמינא חד
אין תרי לא. havah amina chad in trei lo.
Maybe only one? We're saying that we learn from וערכו v'archu two.
So maybe it says do one and then do two, but do
it both in the morning. קא משמע לן דנעביד חד ונעביד תרי?
Kamah mashmalan d'navid chad v'navid trei? Maybe it's telling us have one
כהן Kohen, put up the wood and then have two כהנים Kohanim
put up the wood, but do it both in the morning. גמרא
says, no. If all it was saying was do it twice in
the morning, אם כן נימא קרא ובער ובער ובערו. im kein nima
kra u'bi'er u'bi'er u'bi'eru. So then it just say it in plural
but use the same verb. אי נמי וערך וערכו, Inami v'arach v'archu,
or say arrange arrange, use it in have one singular, one plural,
but use the same verb, and I would have learned do it
twice in the morning, once with one כהן, Kohen, once with two.
מאי ובער וערכו? Mai u'bi'er v'archu? Why when it says twice to
put up wood it uses different verbs? Once it says ובער u'bi'er
and once it says וערכו? v'archu? שמע מינה כדקאמרינן, Shema mina kideka
amrina,
you see it's like we said, that there are two different... periods,
one with the morning sacrifice, one with yesterday, the morning sacrifice gets
one כהן, the afternoon sacrifice gets two כהנים. Kohanim. תני רבי חייא,
Tani Reb Chiya,
רבי חייא Reb Chiya taught, הפיס Ha'payis the lottery, פעמים י"ג, pa'amim
yod gimmel, sometimes it's thirteen people get the lottery. Now we're going
back to not just the limbs of the sacrifice which was nine,
but the whole things that were done with the morning sacrifice, our
earlier משנה Mishna which is thirteen. You'll remember there was the guy
who did the שחיטה, shechita, the guy who did the זריקה, zrika,
right, the guy he did, oh, I just realized I made a
mistake, I got to correct myself. The nine, I just go back
to count, okay, the nine actually does include, yeah because it was
crazy when people do, it does include the flour and the wine.
The things that weren't included in the nine were the things that
preceded the actual bringing of the תמיד, which was the שחיטה, shechita,
the זריקה, zrika,
the cleaning of the מזבח הפנימי mizbe'ach hapnimi and the cleaning of
the מנורה. menorah. Those were the four that weren't listed. When it
said nine for the תמיד, that nine included the flour and the
wine and all of that, which makes a lot of sense. So,
completely erase everything I said before. Okay, anyway, but now we are
saying, so fine, so when we're listing the nine or the ten
or the eleven or the twelve, it's everything that's brought to the
altar, the actual limbs plus the flour, the wine, plus the wood,
plus the incense, whatever it is that is being brought to the
altar. That's when you get from nine to twelve. But now we're
going back and saying if you start at the beginning from the
שחיטה, shechita, the שחיטה, shechita, the זריקה zrika etc., there are thirteen.
That was the earlier משנה. Mishna. Okay, so sometimes you have thirteen,
that's your standard case, the nine with the limbs plus the attendant
issues plus the four that precede, the שחיטה, shechita, the זריקה zrika
and the cleaning of the altar, cleaning of the מנורה. menorah.
פעמים י"ד, pa'amim yod daled, sometimes you'll get to be fourteen. Now
we're just what we're basically doing is taking this משנה Mishna that
has and we're adding the first four. This משנה Mishna says you
can get from nine to twelve, right? But that's nine to twelve
when you start at the bringing of the limbs and the bringing
of everything else that accompanied the limbs. But the four things, there
were four things that preceded. So if you add those four things
that precede, nine to twelve become what? Thirteen to sixteen. Okay, so
פעמים י"ג, pa'amim yod gimmel, פעמים י"ד, pa'amim yod daled, פעמים ט"ו,
pa'amim tet vav, פעמים ט"ז. pa'amim tet zayin. You can get from
thirteen to sixteen. Excellent. It would
be all
as four though, don't you? Why would it be thirteen? You don't,
what? You do the מי שוחט, mi shochet, מי
זורק, mi zorek, מי מדשן, mi medashen, it happens to be thirteen
plus the nine. Right, no, but it could be thirteen or fourteen.
No! Our משנה Mishna right here gives you nine to twelve. Right,
our משנה Mishna is the things that are brought to the מזבח
mizbe'ach is between nine to twelve כהנים, Kohanim, plus the four כהנים
Kohanim that precede gets you thirteen to sixteen. Is that clear to
everybody? Yeah, just add four. והתניא י"ז, Ve'hatanya yod zayin, one minute,
we got a ברייתא that says seventeen! ההיא דלא כרבי אלעזר בן
יעקב אלא כרבי יהודה. Hahi d'lo k'Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov ela k'Rebbi
Yehuda. So remember we had a possibility of one extra, so we
could get one extra, we could say this ties into, oh, there
might be a תנא Tanna that there are five, because if we
actually, you know, can arrange it so that there actually would be
an extra type of a bringing, it's not like I won't work
out the details, but basically we get an extra one in there.
We'll end it here. Okay.